hey episode 12 as you may have noticed
I've got my microphone very close to my
mouth so hopefully this will actually
help solve some of the problems with
volume before josh gets the chance to
come help me set this thing up more
formally
maybe I'll go this way so you can
actually see how cool the microphone is
all right so episode 12 I thought what I
do today is tackle the very fun and
useful concept of phase space this
concept was actually referenced in the
episode around the Kineton framework and
at the end of this I'll loop back and
connecting it back in any frame right
now and just do face based on his own so
Facebook's this takers our model a
bicycle and we're trying to do is we're
trying to get a handle on how to model
the relevant information that describes
some kind of system so in the case of a
bicycle we have about five fundamental
degrees of freedom you've got the
position of the back wheel we've got the
position of the chain we've got the
pedals got the front wheel about the
handlebars and you know absent for
example trying to do things like
position the bike itself and XYZ space
and Teton and maybe position the entire
orientation of the bike in that time in
that space is so four more dimensions
we've pretty much done I said you got
either five dimensions to get the the
space of the state and all those
characteristics or seven more dimensions
if you want to really map this thing
close that was just due to the five so
now what we do is to say okay the
degrees of freedom in each the
dimensions well nicely enough the the
back wheel the chain the pedals and the
front wheel are all just grabbed by
circle so I think they go around and
they repeat the same thing so they're
just a they're a model that describes
and say 360 degrees you can identify
where they are at any point in time and
done so you've got a variable that
describes the the back wheel in terms of
where it is in its rotation around 360
degrees in the chain the pedal in the
front wheel now of course the front
wheel also has the ability to have is a
separate dimensional behavior I can you
can turn and of course the part of the
Barr's do as well so now we have to do
is we have to add another dimension for
the orientation of the front wheel and
the same dimension for the orientation
of the Hana boxes it's a 45 degree
rotation so now with this set of
dimensions in these set of
characteristics we have the ability to
actually fully describe the state of the
bicycle at any point in time so I can
take a spot and I can say okay given the
state so we're around 360 degrees is the
back wheel the chain the pedal front
wheel we're in the 45 degree arc because
that is the front wheel and the
handlebars and that there would be one
point that is the unity or this value of
all of those different dimensions and
that's gonna be the state of the bicycle
unemployment time and then as I move
forward in time where I see is that at
that point we'll move right so basically
will end up happening is the the value
of the 360 degrees for the back wheel
will continue to go MSM peddling it will
go around in a circle and so on that
particular dimension well describes but
if I could be a certain value go from
zero to 360 and they return back to zero
and of course this will happen across
the entire system so what I'll see is
I'll have what's called a traverse
through phase space so phase space is
what describes as a word that it
describes the various dimensions that
we're using and the Traverse is what
what happens as you drive a particular
point through face phase as you ride the
bike you're going to be seeing changes
in all the various variables and
whatever those changes show up as is the
point and when you do that with a normal
bicycle you'll notice a number of things
do you notice two things in particular
one is that you will notice that the
back wheel the chain and the pedals seem
to be entrained which is to say that
there is some strict correlation if it's
a simple bicycle a very strict
correlation between those states so that
as the state in the back wheel changes
the state had changed chain changes and
the state in the pedals change and in
some fixed ratio so in some sense
are the same and they are entrained most
likely you will notice that there is
more of a correlation between the state
of the front wheel in the back wheel
meaning that because they are not deeply
deeply causally connected although they
are somewhat causally connected about
the fact that they're both on the ground
and they're both connected by the
chassis you'll see that there is a high
quality relationship between the state
of the front wheel on the back wheel but
it may not be as tight as the
relationship between said the pedals and
the back wheel but when you will see is
that there is a tight entrainment
between the handlebars in the front
wheel and I mean when you turn the
handlebars one do we didn't left the
front wheel also choice one degrees left
if you've got a well function your bike
okay so that's that's it like that's the
concept so so now let's take this and be
a little bit more robust so try to
imagine constructing a phase space to
describe say a horse well you're going
to notice I think two things the first
is that it's enormously larger face
space because we're dealing with
something which is has vastly more
degrees of freedom so we're not just
talking about say the the state of each
two legs and a head in the tail we might
also have to model and for example the
state of the blood pressure and the
circulation of the pumping of the heart
or the dilation of the eye not the total
number of possible states the district
necessary to describe of course is
qualitatively enormous now of course we
can decide to do a sampling so you know
we're just going to model say the
positions of the legs and be done with
it they can simplify the model a lot and
that's a very useful thing to do but the
first observation is that you're dealing
with something like an evolved organism
you're dealing with just an enormous
amount face space in comparison to a
designed object like a bicycle the
second thing that you'll notice is that
what you may not notice it the soldiers
tell you is that the phase space of a
bicycle is finite and bounded which is
to say that so long as it is still a
bicycle the dimensions that I just
described is what they are and the
variables that they can they can take
aren't changing so you're not having
361 degrees suddenly
merging in your bicycle wheel it's just
commuters 60 degrees and that's all it
is by contrast in the horse the phase
space is in fact not bounded meaning
that in time in relationship to its
environment the horse can actually
change the shape of his phase space and
new kinds of possible variables can
emerge inside certain dimensionality
it's the say for example the horse
changes its gait in response to the
environment that it's in and this
emerges is something that has never
happened before in that particular horse
run horses in general this is all
possible of course it have that capacity
and in fact in principle one can
actually imagine the emergence of
entirely new degrees of freedom
entirely new dimensionalities obviously
in the situation of evolution which is
this happen all the time like the
emergence of light-sensitive cells is
entirely novel but that didn't exist and
then it did it's a pretty entirely new
portion of face base not just the value
values that it can handle and so the
idea here is that now we're connecting
back to the Kineton framework a
complicated system is the system but has
a finite and bounded phase space so
bicycles and airplanes a complex system
is the system that does not it has an
unbounded phase space and I think that's
that's pretty much it
so with this new concept we're going to
be able to do other stuff in the future
but for now I think that's all we have
to do